<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[personal | Divya Manian]]></title>
  <link href="http://nimbupani.github.com/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://nimbupani.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-23T21:00:32+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://nimbupani.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Divya Manian]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving to SF]]></title>
    <link href="http://nimbupani.github.com/moving-to-sf.html"/>
    <updated>2012-03-27T08:18:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://nimbupani.github.com/moving-to-sf</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As of today, I am no longer an employee of Opera.</p>

<p>It has been a great ride. Being a web opener and doing things I did at Opera was one of the goals I set out to accomplish 6 years ago. It is time for a new challenge, and a new beginning.</p>

<p>I will be moving to San Fransisco, to work for <a href="http://blogs.adobe.com/webplatform/">Adobe's Webplatform team</a>, creating things to showcase Adobe's Web Standard proposals and more. This will hopefully mean less of me telling you what to do, and more of putting my money where my mouth is!</p>

<p>It is almost a cliché to thank your ex-employers, but Opera has been the most fun workplace, so far. My boss <a href="https://twitter.com/andreasbovens">Andreas Bovens</a> has been most supporting, pragmatic and fun person to work with (yes yes, <a href="https://twitter.com/oDevRel">Devrel team</a> you all too!). The DevRel team has distinguished musicians among them too, bringing you lovely catchy numbers like the <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SFvYhEhFsdQ">Web Standards Hoedown</a>, <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5b7dNNapMCM">CSS3 Song</a> and <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7gNmFabAOGc">more</a>!</p>

<p>It would be remiss of me to not highlight all the brilliant people at Opera who have been of great help: <a href="http://twitter.com/hzr">David Håsäther</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/__chris__">Christian Krebs</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/foolip">Philip Jägenstedt</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/annevk">Anne van Kesteren</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/zcorpan">Simon Pieters</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/101664973349222017745/posts">James Graham</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/gsnedders">Geoffrey Snedders</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/lachy">Lachlan Hunt</a> (who made this <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qmJKhois7E8">awesome video</a> that needs to be inflicted on everyone), <a href="http://twitter.com/richtibett">Rich Tibett</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/p01">Mathieu Henri</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/erikjmoller">Erik Möller</a>, and the amazing Open Web QA team: <a href="http://twitter.com/hallvord">Hallvord R. M. Steen</a>, <a href="http://www.kleiven.org/ola/">Ola</a>.</p>

<p>I can't wait to start work with my new team at Adobe (headed by <a href="http://twitter.com/vincent_hardy">Vincent Hardy</a>). I suppose moving to SF is like moving to Mordor in some ways, but if you have any tips and suggestions on living in SF, please do tell!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
